Boker tov בוקר טוב Boker tov and good מועדים לשמחה. Moadim l'simcha.
Thank you. Okay, so today's דף daf should be ס"ג, Samech-Gimmel, but
בחסדי השם b'chasdei Hashem we're a little bit דף daf behind, so
we're on ס"ב Samech-Bet and we are moving on to the משנה.
Mishnah. We had a whole discussion about מעשה ידיים maaseh yadayim and
a wife's domestic duties. ברוך אתה ה' אלוקינו מלך העולם שהכל נהיה
בדברו.
Baruch ata Hashem Elokeinu Melech Ha'olam
shehakol nihiya
bidvaro.
And
now we are turning on to the question about the husband's responsibility
specifically of עונה. onah. So the משנה Mishnah first spoke about a
man who takes a vow not to have sex with his wife,
give him one week or two weeks.
Then we have a whole issue about a whole list of who
can apparently leave without express permission from their wives. It's assumed that
even though people have a regular amount that they're at the house,
occasionally they have to be out longer. So students, presumably תורה Torah
students, have a right to be out for תלמוד תורה, talmud torah,
it says, presumably for a month without express permission. And workers for
a week. So even though as the משנה Mishnah is going to
detail their obligations of עונה onah might be more frequent, nevertheless, sometimes
there's a business deal or sometimes you gotta go visit the רבי
Rebbe or whatever, you gotta go travel for business. So there's a
certain amount of latitude that's allowed and then the end of the
משנה Mishnah gives a whole list based on a person's profession and
therefore how frequently they're at home and the amount of energy that
they have determines the frequency of the מצווה mitzvah of עונה. onah.
It ends curiously with דברי רבי אליעזר. divrei Rabbi Eliezer. There's nobody
exactly arguing on him. So what do you mean דברי רבי אליעזר,
divrei Rabbi Eliezer, we'll get to that in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay,
but the גמרא Gemara then started with the issue about what if
you get
express permission from one's wife, what's appropriate? אורחא דמילתא קמ"ל Orcha d'milsa
kama the beginning of ס"ב עמוד א', Samech-Bet amud aleph, which is
itself a fascinating question because the גמרא Gemara says if you got
permission, you got permission. What else is there other than legal permission?
And the גמרא Gemara says well there might be legal permission, but
the question is what's appropriate and there's a very important רש"י, Rashi,
I don't know if it was read yesterday. If you look at
the first רש"י Rashi on ס"ב עמוד א', Samech-Bet amud aleph, אורחא
דמילתא, Orcha d'milsa, דרך ארץ שלא ישא עליו חטא ואפילו הוא יכול
לפתותה שתתן לו רשות.
derech eretz shelo yisa alav
cheit, v'afillu hu yachol l'pattosa shetitein lo reshus. Meaning even if the
husband can persuade the wife to give permission, there's permission and there's
permission. There's sort of like very actively encouraging it or talking her
into it. And רש"י Rashi even points out that there's a moral
aspect here which is not a legal aspect. לא ישא עליו חטא,
lo yisa alav cheit, right? That's very powerful language that there you'll
be you'll bear the burden of a sin if you persuaded your
wife to do something that at the end of the day she
really wouldn't have wanted to go along with. So I think that's
a very important in terms of general about thinking about the law,
הלכה halakha and morality and so on and the language that רש"י
Rashi uses. And the גמרא Gemara quoted two opinions, the opinions of
רב Rav that said a month here and a month at home,
a month away and a month at home, and the opinion of
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said a month away and two months at
home. And they quoted various פסוקים. psukim. And then the גמרא Gemara
had a parallel debate about
אנחה שובר חצי גופו? anachah shever chatzi gufo? No.
Okay, so let's take a look. אמר רב, Amar Rav, so says
רב. Rav. So now we're about ten lines down at the asterisk.
So the same way we had that debate of רב Rav and
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, we have the following debate of רב Rav
and רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. And I should say that today's דף
daf or yesterday's דף daf that we're doing today is an ongoing
reflection on the sort of pull between a man's responsibility
at home, whether it's specifically עונה onah or just in general his
presence at home and his responsibility to his wife, and his responsibility
towards תלמוד תורה. talmud torah. Nowadays a lot of people experience this,
right? People that are workaholics and married to their work are not
sufficiently at home and so on. Often it's the man, not always,
but specifically in the גמרא Gemara it was a more interesting reflection
when you talk about competing religious responsibilities and the responsibility towards תלמוד
תורה talmud torah and the responsibility of a man towards his wife.
Daniel Boyarin has a whole book about like the eroticism of תלמוד
תורה talmud torah and whatever and in some place calls תורה Torah
like the other woman in the marriage. So anyway, so that's going
to be sort of like the ongoing issue here, right? Because the
משנה Mishnah starts with you can
go out once a week and then it says, okay, but
how much would you be allowed to go out if you really
like persuaded or if you wanted to talk her into it, and
trying to say even if she would agree, you could get her
to agree to more, there might be some appropriate limits, which is
balancing what you want to be doing in terms of your religious
and תורה Torah pursuits towards even if you have technical, legal rights
to do it, your real fundamental responsibility at home. Okay, so that's
like important to realize that that's going to be the ongoing dynamic
through today's דף daf with different types of coming out in different
places on that. So the גמרא Gemara says now like this, אמר
רב, Amar Rav, אנחה, anachah, so we had a debate of רב
Rav and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan based on a פסוק, pasuk, we're
going to have another debate. אנחה שובר חצי גופו של אדם. anachah
shever chatzi gufo shel adam.
Moaning, sighing, breaks half of the... son's body. שנאמר, She'ne'emar, ואתה בן
אדם, Ve'atah ben adam, now you son of man, האנח בשברון מתנים,
he'anach beshivron motnayim,
moan or you know wail, moan on the with the breaking of
the thighs of the loins, ובמרירות תאנה, u'vemerirut te'anech,
and with bitterness you shall moan. And on the hearing and because
God is telling him about the eventual destruction of the בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash. רבי יוחנן אמר אף כל גופו של אדם, Rabbi Yochanan
amar af kol gufo shel adam, no,
it destroys the entire body. שנאמר, She'ne'emar, והיה כי יאמרו אליך על
מה אתה נאנח, vehaya ki yomru eilecha al mah atah ne'enach, they
will say to you, why are you moaning? ואמרת אל השמועה כי
באה, ve'amarta el hashemuah ki va'ah, because the hearing of the reports
of destruction of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. ונמס כל לב, venamas
kol lev,
and all hearts of have melted, ורפו כל ידיים, verafu kol yadayim,
and all hands have been weakened, וכהתה כל רוח, vechahatah kol ruach,
and all spirit have been dulled, וכל ברכיים תלכנה מים, vechol birkayim
telechnah mayim,
and all the you know knees turn into water. So anyway, the
entire body dissolves and is destroyed. שרבי יוחנן נמי הכתיב בשברון מתנים?
She'Rabbi Yochanan nami hachativ beshivron motnayim? It says the breaking of the
thighs, only half the body, the middle of the body. So he
says no, ההיא דכי מתחלה ממתנים מתחלה. hahi de'chi matchala mimotnayim matchala.
When it starts, it starts by the thighs, the loins, but it
spreads and destroys the whole body. ורב נמי הכתיב ונמס כל לב
ורפו כל ידיים? VeRav nami hachativ venamas kol lev verafu kol yadayim?
All hearts, you know, will melt, which is like the entire, וכהתה
כל רוח, vechahatah kol ruach, and the whole spirit will dim. No,
שאני שמועת בית המקדש, shani shemuat Beis HaMikdash, that was when they
heard about the destruction of the Temple, דתקיפה טובא. detakifa tuva. That's
very, you know, that's very strong,
that's very, you know, desolate, but otherwise it would not be that
bad. Now, let's hear a little story about this and then I
want to say something about how this connects to the earlier issue.
ההוא ישראל ועכו"ם דהוו קאזלי באורחא, Hahu Yisrael ve'akum de'havu ka'azlei be'orcha,
a Jew and a non-Jew were going on the way, בהדי הדדי,
bahadi hadadi, together. לא אמטי עכו"ם לסגויי בהדי ישראל. Lo amti akum
lisguyei bahadi Yisrael. The non-Jew did not have the strength to keep
up to the Jew, the Jew was walking so fast.
אדדכר חורבן בית המקדש, Ad dicheir churban Beis HaMikdash, he said to
the to the Jew said, oh remember you don't have a Temple.
So נגיד ואתנח, nagid ve'itnach, so he like he, you know, he
moaned and he and he, you know, sighed. ואפילו הכי לא אמטי
עכו"ם לסגויי בהדיה. Ve'afilu hachi lo amti akum lisguyei bahadei. So
that slowed him down, but even with that, the non-Jew wasn't able
to keep up with him. אמר ליה לאו אמריתו, Amar lei lav
amritu, one minute, I learned in גמרא כתובות Gemara Kesuvos in the
דף יומי Daf Yomi that didn't you guys say that אנחה שוברת
חצי גופו של אדם, anacha shoveres chatzi gufo shel adam,
that a sigh breaks half of a person's body? אמר ליה הני
מילי מילתא חדתא, Amar lei hanei milei milta chadeti, that's when it's
like a new report, like something, you know, some new tragedy that
we've just heard about. אבל הא דדשנן בה, Aval ha de'dashnan bah,
this that we've done, you know, that we're sort of used to,
that we've trampled over, you know, where we've heard this before, right?
So this,
right, so you know, so we're inured to this. דאמרי אינשי, De'amri
inshei, because people say, למלפי תיכלי לא בעתא, lemalfi tichli lo ba'ata,
a woman who suffers—it's a very terrible
comparison—a woman who suffers many miscarriages, לא בעתא, lo ba'ata, does not
have the same fear from the next miscarriage because she's already, you
know, experienced. So we've gotten a lot of suffering thanks to you
non-Jews, so hearing about what happened in the past is not going
to do anything to us, we're inured to it. Now, you could
just say this is an interesting little parallel רב Rav and רבי
יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, but to me it seems, especially as we're going
to see in the next going גמרות, Gemoros, that there is a
very clear tie-in here between the earlier sayings. So as we're about
to get into the גמרות Gemoros that some of you might be
aware of that deal with, you know, you know the famous story—whatever
made recently re-famous, if people didn't know it already, by, you know,
by Ruth Calderon—about the rabbi, the wife who sighs when the husband
doesn't come back on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, and the, you know,
the roof breaks in and he dies. So we're about to get
the whole so stories about like roofs breaking in and people sighing
and the consequences of the husband not returning home when he's supposed
to be learning תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah. Now remember, רב Rav said
you could be out one, you know, half the time, one month
away, one month at home. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan demanded that the
guy be home more often. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said one month
away and two months at home. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is
a little, is more sensitive to ensure that your תלמוד תורה Talmud
Torah does not take you too much out of your house. By
the way, this connects to a larger issue between the debates of
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and בבל, Bavel, both about marriage and about,
not surprisingly, the relationship of marriage to תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah. ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael was already a monogamous society
and one also in, in which people were also a little bit
financially, well, whatever, but it was a monogamous society, whereas בבל Bavel
was polygamous. ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, they seem to more give intrinsic
value to marriage, whereas in בבל, Bavel, this marriage was more instrumental.
You got married so it would free up the husband to allow
him to go and learn תורה, Torah, or marriage prevented the man
in בבל Bavel from having illicit sexual thoughts or acting on those
illicit sexual thoughts, whereas in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, you find statements
like כל אדם שאינו שרוי בלא אשה שרוי בלא טובה, kol adam
she'eino shari belo isha shari belo tova, you know, לא טוב היות
האדם לבדו, lo tov heyos ha'adam levado, more of an intrinsic sense
of. value of marriage and less instrumental. Similarly, the famous debate in
the גמרא Gemara in קידושין Kiddushin whether a person should first get
married and then learn תורה Torah or first learn תורה Torah and
then get married. In בבל Bavel they basically said, get married and
then learn תורה, Torah, because you're married, so you have an outlet
for your sexual desire, and then you go learn תורה. Torah. And
in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they said, no, once you're married, ריחיים
בצוארו. reichaim betzavaro. Once you're married you have responsibilities at home. So
if you're going to get married, you can't just ignore your wife
and go learn תורה, Torah, you have to prioritize those responsibilities. So
you'd better learn תורה Torah before you get married, because once you
get married that's where your primary responsibilities are going to be. So
in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they actually gave more weight to the
and that you see in רבי יוחנן: Rabbi Yochanan: two months at
home, one month away for תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah. רב Rav is
saying, no, one month at home, one month away for תלמוד תורה.
Talmud Torah. One minute. So there is already setting up an important
debate between רב Rav and רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, which is really
a deeper debate of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and בבל Bavel about
marriage and about marriage and תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah. So it is
not at all surprising to me, I haven't seen anybody else who
says this, but to me it seems quite obvious that that's the
issue about the moaning, right? רב Rav says, okay, your wife's at
home, she's moaning, she's upset you're not there, it's only חצי גופו
של אדם. chatzi gufo shel adam.
She'll survive. You spend your time learning תורה. Torah. רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan says, no, כל גופו של אדם. kol gufo shel adam.
If that's if that's the way your absence, if your absence has
that impact on her, then that's that can be totally destructive to
her and to the marriage and whatever and you cannot allow that
to happen. So this idea of sighing, and we're going to see
sighing in a minute in the גמרא, Gemara, to me is very
much about how do you assess what is the impact of my
absence? And of course how you assess what the impact of your
absences are are always done, are often done through the lens of
your own biases and assumptions, right? So if you think certain things
about marriage and certain things about תלמוד תורה, Talmud Torah, then okay,
they'll survive.
If you think about other things, they're not going to survive, you
have to be at home. And by the way, I don't think
it's surprising also the line at the end, which is once you
get used to it we can survive, which also could be the
בבל Bavel response to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Whatever you think about
it, here in בבל Bavel the wives are used to it. They're
used to sending off their husbands and staying at home, being left
with the domestic responsibilities. And we find by the way that ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael criticized
the Babylonian rabbis who abandoned their wives to go learn תורה, Torah,
but maybe a response is that's all very nice and you have
different standards, but here our wives are used to it, so however
destructive this can be, once you're used to it things are different.
And that could be the ending of this story, yes.
Wasn't רב Rav living in בבל, Bavel, the rabbi with the temporary
wives?
Yeah, that's also true.
Okay, so that fits as well. Okay, so now let's keep that
in mind because that's going to be a theme that's going to
recur.
הטיילים בכל יום. Hatayalin bechol yom. Now the tourists or whatever טיילים
tayalin means, as we'll see in a minute what it means, they
every day have a מצות עונה mitzvat onah when the wife isn't
a נדה. niddah. Interesting discussions by the way of how does the
fact of נדה niddah impact the מצות עונה, mitzvat onah, because in
the time of the גמרא Gemara נדה niddah was just
one week out of the month, nowadays it's close to two weeks
out of the month. So you have to adjust the
עונה onah obligation accordingly.
מאי טיילים? Mai tayalin? Who are these טיילים tayalin that every day
have a מצות עונה? mitzvat onah? אמר
רבא בני פרקי. Amar Rava bnei pirkei. Those that come and study
at the ישיבה, Yeshiva, they study at a local ישיבה. Yeshiva. אמר
ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, so then they go home every single
day and they're not worn out from their work, from their labor,
so they have a מצות עונה mitzvat onah every
day, assuming the wife is interested in it. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye,
אביי Abaye said, מאן דכתיב בהו, man dechtiv behu,
those, meaning the wives, of whom it's written regarding them we'll see
what this means, שוא לכם משכימי קום, Shav lachem mashkimei kum, woe
to you those who, or it's meaningless to you those who get
up early to go to work, מאחרי שבת, me'acharei shevet, and postpone
Sabbath or אוכלי לחם העצבים, ochlei lechem ha'atzavim, and eat bread of
anguish.
כן יתן
לידידו שנא. Ken yitein liyidido shena. God will give the reward לידידו
liyidido to his dear one. I mean, that's the way the גמרא
Gemara is reading this. ואמר רב יצחק, Ve'amar Rav Yitzchak, אלו נשותיהם
של תלמידי חכמים. eilu neshoteihem shel talmidei chachamim. Who's going to get
the real reward? Not those that are getting up really early in
order to make money. No, those are getting up really early to
learn תורה Torah and their wives who are supporting them. אלו נשותיהם
של תלמידי חכמים שמנדדות שינה מעיניהם. eilu neshoteihem shel talmidei chachamim shemenadedot
shena me'eineihem. They the sleep is removed from their eyes בעולם הזה.
ba'olam hazeh. That's ידידו מנדדות, yidido menadedot, not just
beloved ones, but those that lose sleep in this world וזוכות לחיי
עולם הבא vezochot lechayei Olam HaBa and they get reward in the
world to come. So basically here again we have the students are
off learning and the wives are at home and they're working to
the bone in order to enable their husbands to learn, but again
this is a בבל Bavel take on all of this,
but they're going to get their reward in עולם הבא. Olam HaBa.
So therefore, how can so how can you therefore say that the
מצוות עונה mitzvah onah is each day? Why not? Well, because if
they're if
they're if they're losing sleep, that means they're staying up late at
night, that means their husbands aren't coming home till late at night.
So if the wives are working so hard and the husbands are
coming home so late, who's having sex every day? So the גמרא
Gemara says, ואת אמרת בני פרקי? ve'at amart benei pirkei? אלא אמר
אביי. Ela amar Abaye. Abaye says that can't be. They're working too
hard to do that. כדרב, Kederav, like Rav. At least the wives
are working hard. דאמר רב כגון רב שמואל בר שילת דאכל מדידיה.
De'amar Rav kegon Rav Shmuel bar Shilat de'achal midideih. No, it's people
that are independently wealthy but, you know, also maybe you know, live
a,
we'll see, like a non-ostentatious life. כגון רב שמואל בר שילת דאכל
מדידיה, Kegon Rav Shmuel bar Shilat de'achal midideih, he eats of his
own, you know, sort of he doesn't have to borrow money, he
eats off of his own labor, ושתי מדידיה וגני בטולא דאפדניה, veshati
midideih vegani betulla de'apadneih, and he eats and drinks of his own,
you know, earnings and he sleeps in the shade of his of
his home, of his castle, ולא
חליף פרסטקא דמלכא אבביה, velo chalif peristaka demalka avaveih, but the tax
collector of the king does not pass by his door, meaning because
he does it in a low-key way, he doesn't attract attention of
the government. So he has the best. He's earned, you know, he's
got his own money, he's he has an independent like, you know,
he's got a trust fund but he doesn't spend the money in
an ostentatious way so he's free from governmental responsibilities. So somebody who
basically doesn't have to work for a living and doesn't have to
be responsible for other types of, you know, of other issues, so
that type of a person the מצוות עונה mitzvah onah is every
single day. There's, you know, they're not ex- they're not doing any,
they're not working too hard. So now the גמרא Gemara says, כי
אתא רבין, Ki ata Ravin, when Ravin came from ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, he said כגון
מפנקי דמערבא, kegon mefankei dema'arava, like the, like the, you know,
what's the word of מפונק, mefunack, like not spoiled, but like the,
not delicate, what? Pampered.
What? Pampered. Pampered.
Oh, that's a good one. The pampered ones of ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. Okay, and now we're going to see what this means. It
actually, you know, could be just means the wealthy ones, but now
actually we're going to have an interesting discussion about rabbis. Okay, but
same idea. It's talking about wealthy, independently wealthy people who don't work
for a living. רבי אבהו הווה קאי בבי באני. Rabbi Abbahu hava
kai bevei bane. Rabbi Abbahu was in a bathhouse. הווה סמכי ליה
תרי עבדי. Hava samchi leh terei avdei. Two of his students were
supporting him because presumably he was very heavy, very, or you know.
By the way, I think Yaakov Elman talks about the fact about
how בבל Bavel imagines like because if you see you know all
of these like you know these like Eastern paintings or whatever, you
know, the sort of rulers are very fat,
very large, because of course that's what you do, you eat a
lot of food, right? So apparently that's also how in בבל Bavel
they imagined the rabbis of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Whether it actually
was accurate or not, but they imagined them through this oriental lens,
through this, you know. So anyway, so there he was, he was
being supported by these two servants.
איפחית בי באני מיתותיה. Ifchis bei bane mituseih. So the bathhouse floor
broke underneath him, and it would have gone right into like, you
know, the way you got steam is there was a whole room
underneath the sauna that they had boiling water. So the floor of
the sauna broke through and he would have fallen into the boiling
water. איתרמי ליה עמודא, Isrami leh amuda, but he managed to like,
you know, the he was to have a pillar. Like a pillar
happened his way. He managed caught himself on a pillar.
You can see those in you can see those.
The pillars that support the floor, exactly.
Like in מצדה, Metzada, there's a picture of מצדה Metzada where the
floor is no longer there and
you can see the pillars. Makes sense. You have a room, a
space, the room underneath where the water's being heated and the floor
is supported by the pillars. So he managed to catch himself on
a pillar. Charlie's got the picture.
Okay. סליק, Salik, so he managed to pull himself up, ואסקיהו, ve'askeihu,
and he also pulled up his two servants that were that had
been supporting him until that point. Similarly, רבי יוחנן הווה קסליק בדרגא.
Rabbi Yochanan hava kasalik bedarga. He was going up on a step.
הווה סמכי
ליה רב אמי ורב אסי. Hava samchi leh Rav Ami veRav Assi.
Rav Ami and Rav Assi were supporting him. איפחית דרגא תותיה. Ifchis
darga tuseih. The step broke underneath him. סליק, Salik, so he managed
to catch himself on the other surviving steps or whatever, וסליק, vesalik,
he pulled himself up, ואסקיהו, ve'askeihu, and he pulled them up with
him. So here he has these rabbis who are being supported by
these other, by these others, now they're pulling the other these others
up. So אמרו ליה רבנן, Amru leh rabbanan, so the rabbis said
to them, מכדי אחרי דהכי, michdei acharei dehachi, if you're so strong
that you can pull us up, so למה ליה למסמכיה? lama leh
lemismacheih? So why or they said, if that you can pull them
up, why do you need other people to support you? אמר להו,
Amar lehu, they said to them, אם כן מה אני מניח לזקנה?
im ken ma ani mani'ach lezikna? Because I have to preserve my
strength. If I use up all my strength now, what's going to
be left for me for old age? So, you know, I tried
to tell my wife that's why I wasn't going to the gym,
you know, but it didn't work. I gotta I gotta stay on
the couch, I gotta preserve my strength, you know, but anyway, so
I'm not sure it really works that way. Anyway. Okay, so this
was like a little humorous interlude because it talks about מפנקי דמערבא.
mefankei dema'arava. But I do want to make a point, which is,
I mean I'm already anticipating the גמרא Gemara we're going to say,
I spoke about the roof breaking and the rabbi falling in and
dying, so here you have another story of something breaking, right, of
the floor breaking underneath. But we're going to find out later that
in the ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael story of the floor breaking underneath
was what happens when you're being so negligent to your responsibilities to
your wife, you know, because you're off learning תורה Torah and the
floor's going to break and the rabbi's going to die, right, that's
that story that we're coming up to. Here, it's a story about
the rabbis of ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, right, the rabbis were רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and who else was it here? רבי אבהו, Rabbi
Abahu, right, rabbis of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael who are not being
not responsible to their wives, right, they're the ones that are spending
more time at home. So the story here about the floor breaking
underneath is a completely different story, right? It has nothing to do
with that. So you have these two different versions of the floor
breaking underneath, here it's a story about how strong they were, as
opposed to a very different story of a floor breaking underneath that
we're about to read. Okay.
And the floor breaks underneath, he used the עמוד Amud to support.
He's still an עמוד. Amud.
Oh, he said I mean metaphorically, so you've got yeah, you've still
got that support, that's a nice point. That's a very nice point.
Okay so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. והפועלים שתים בשבת,
V'hapolim shtayim bashabbas, the workers twice a week. ותניא פועל אחת בשבת,
V'tanya poel achas bashabbas, so sort of like day workers, day laborers,
don't we teach that that means like or craftsmen or something, don't
we teach that that's once a week, we have the ברייתא Braita
and not twice a week? אמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא לא קשיא
כאן בעושה מלאכה בעירו כאן בעושה מלאכה בעיר אחרת. Amar Rabbi Yosi
berabi Chanina lo kashya kan be'osei melacha b'irono kan be'osei melacha b'ir
acheres. Are they working in their town or in a different town?
So if they're working in the town, then they have more energy
and strength and they're more at home, so it's twice a week.
If they have to do some commuting even if they come go
back and forth on the same day, which it seems to be
is the case, nevertheless, they're more worn out.
תניא נמי הכי והפועלים שתים בשבת במה דברים אמורים בעושה מלאכה בעירו
אבל עושה מלאכה בעיר אחרת אחת בשבת, Tanya nami hachi v'hapolim shtayim
bashabbas bameh devarim amurim be'osei melacha b'irono aval osei melacha b'ir acheres
achas bashabbas, and only once a week, excuse me, twice a week,
once a week, I said month I meant week. Yes.
I read as the reason here if you're doing day laborer stuff
of the town you
have to come back every other night.
Every other night. Yeah. You have to come back it's not necessarily
that you come back every night
but you're tired, but you're not even coming back every night.
There's restrictions here like all these people who travel for work, the
idea is yes sure you can travel for work but you have
to
arrange it so that you don't travel too much. Right, so you
only so you alternate which nights you're home or something. Yeah that
could be as well. Okay, so there you have between once a
week or twice a week and then you have the guys that
are daily, but normal people once a week tends to be the
standard. החמורים אחת בשבת, Hachamorim achas bashabbat, the donkey drivers once a
week. אמר ליה רבה בר רב חנן לאביי, Amar lei Rabba bar
Rav Chanan l'Abaye, איכא דתני לאשמועינן טייל ופועל, Ika d'tana l'ashmian tayal
u'poel,
so he's saying like this, the משנה Mishnah we have that if
a guy takes a נדר Neder not to have sex with his
wife, so according to בית הלל, Beis Hillel, after a week basically
he's got to divorce his wife, or if the נדר Neder was
for a week he's got to divorce his wife. So the גמרא
Gemara says one minute, you know, if you look in the משנה,
Mishnah, not too many people had a עונה Ona responsibility more than
once a week, right? You only had basically these independently wealthy people
which were every day and these פועלים Poalim which were twice a
week, but most people were really once a week or less,
so what's the big deal if the guy took a נדר Neder
not to have sex for a week, that so he missed one
עונה, Ona, he has to divorce his wife? I mean, so is
the whole teaching of the case of the נדר Neder just for
the טייל Tayal and פועל? Poel? Just for the people that are
twice a week or every day? Those are the people that the
נדר Neder makes a difference to, everybody else in the משנה Mishnah
the נדר Neder doesn't make a difference because it can't understand, because
if the guy took a נדר Neder for one week, big deal,
he only misses one עונה, Ona, what's the big deal? So that's
why he has to divorce his wife? אמר ליה, Amar lei, he
said לא, Lo, it applies to everything, it applies even to the
הגמל, Hagamal, the camel driver, even to the guy who only has
a responsibility once every six months, nevertheless if he takes a נדר
Neder to be off sex for one week, he has to divorce
his wife. Why? והא ששה חדשים קאמר, V'ha shisha chodashim ka'amar, he
has his obligation is only every six months, why would that נדר
Neder make a difference? No, אינו דומה מי שיש לו פת בסלו
למי שאין לו פת בסלו. Eino domeh mi sheyesh lo pas besalo
l'mi she'ein lo pas besalo. It's not different somebody who has bread
in the basket for somebody who doesn't have bread in the basket.
So if the wife knows that the husband is in theory available
to have sex with her at any time, or even if he's
away but there's no real restriction other than the fact that he's
currently not present, then it's not the same as the fact that
there actually is a נדר Neder that is making it not possible.
And for that נדר Neder even for a נדר Neder of just
one week, even if somebody who normally they don't have sex that
frequently, that is enough of a distancing of the marriage, of a
separating of the couple that would demand a divorce. You cannot live
that way.
It's a funny application of this expression.
Why the גמרא Gemara always uses it for sex. I mean...
No, usually it means that the person is present, here it means
if the person is legally not present.
Exactly, that's true, that is true, right. That's a good point, that's
correct. Okay, אמר ליה רבה
בר רב חנן לאביי,
Amar lei
Rabba bar Rav Chanan l'Abaye, חמור ונעשה גמל מאי?
Chamor
vena'aseh gamal mai?
Now. What if you want to
switch your jobs? What if you're a donkey, a camel, a donkey
driver and you want to become a camel driver? So take you
out of the house more often, maybe you'll earn more money but
you'll be less available, you know, for your wife. So are you
legally allowed to do this without your wife's permission? Okay, so, so
what's the הלכה? halakhah? So חמר ונעשה גמל מאי? Chamor ve-naseh gamal
mai? אמר ליה רוצה אשה בקב ותיפלות מעשרה קבין ופרישות. Amar lei
rotzah ishah be-kav ve-tiflut me-asarah kabin u-frishut. So this again is a,
you could have said this in the answer in a very different
way. You could say you don't have the right, you have a
primary responsibility to your wife and being at home unless she agrees,
but the גמרא Gemara says that by sort of by saying by
making a negative statement about women. And it says, a woman would
rather have one measure and תיפלות tiflut and more sort of opportunities
for sex is essentially what it's saying, than ten measures and more
asceticism. So therefore the wife doesn't care that you're earning more money,
you know, she's more, she'd rather have less money and more sex.
Okay, but the word it uses for sex, תיפלות, tiflut, is like
trivial things and it doesn't say she wants your presence more than,
you know, your money. She speaks, so it's, it's funny the way
the גמרא Gemara says it. I mean in the end it's saying
you don't have a right to do it without your wife's permission,
but it's doing it by sort of by this more, you know,
negative statement about women and their values. By the way, the רא"ש
Rosh makes a, going back to this whole תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah
issue, you know, the רא"ש Rosh makes a point and the רא"ש
Rosh says, but let's say you want to become a, want to
go and learn תורה. Torah. So are you, do you need your
wife's permission? And it says no, that you don't need your wife's
permission for. So if you want to go and learn תורה Torah
even if that's going to take you more out of the house,
that you don't need permission for, that you're entitled to do. I
don't see it's a negative statement necessarily.
I mean, it echoes to me רוצה אדם בקב שלו מתשעה קבין
של חברו, rotzeh adam be-kav shelo mi-tishah kabin shel chavero, which is
something that what is more satisfying to you.
Yeah,
the word תיפלות tiflut is the problem.
What?
Well plus,
תיפלות tiflut can also be like to be טפל tafel to someone,
to be attached or to be hanging off of something else.
No, that's with a ט. tet. With a ת, tav, תיפלות tiflut
is like, you know, I don't know, I mean, you know, it's
like what is it like, כל המלמד בתו תורה כאילו מלמדה תיפלות,
kol ha-melamed bitto Torah ke-ilu melamdah tiflut, right? So there's clearly a
negative, right, you could have said it if you would have used
a different word other than תיפלות, tiflut, you could, you know, the
word, it's the word תיפלות tiflut that's a little bit of the
problem. Okay, הספנים אחת לשישה חודשים. ha-sapanim achat le-shishah chodashim.
Now ship or sailors or whatever, once every six months, דברי רבי
אליעזר. divrei Rabbi Eliezer. Now רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer was did the
end of this whole משנה. Mishnah. Now what was רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer going on? Did the Rabbis disagree with the frequency? What is
the implicit opposing opinion to רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer? So let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara. So אמר רב ברונא אמר רב
הלכה כרבי אליעזר, Amar Rav Bruna Amar Rav halakhah ke-Rabbi Eliezer, we
rule like רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. Okay, what's the other opinion? אמר
רב אדא בר אהבה אמר רב זו דברי רבי אליעזר. Amar Rav
Adda bar Ahava Amar Rav zu divrei Rabbi Eliezer. Now we're going
to find out, this is the opinion of רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer.
אבל חכמים אומרים התלמידים יוצאין לתלמוד תורה ב' וג' שנים שלא ברשות.
Aval Chachamim omrim ha-talmidim yotzin le-Talmud Torah be' ve-gimel shanim shelo bi-reshut.
So if you wanted to know about the idea of the tension
between תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah and being at home, so more than
the רב Rav and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that we saw before
about one month home, one month away, etc., here we find that
the גמרא Gemara is saying רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, the debate of
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is not about the whole משנה Mishnah about
the general frequency of עונה. onah. The arguing opinion about רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer specifically is about how far, long a תורה Torah student
can be away without permission from his wife. And actually the opposing
position is as long as you want, two or three years. So
you really see this idea of weighing totally in favor of תלמוד
תורה Talmud Torah against somebody's domestic responsibilities. Now before we get on
to the תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah versus the home, I just want
to say parenthetically that it actually is possible that the other
opposing opinion to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, other than what the גמרא
Gemara says, which it's not going to explore here but gets explored
elsewhere, is how fundamentally you conceptualize עונה. onah. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
in the משנה Mishnah conceptualizes עונה onah as a certain frequency. Once
a week, twice a week, once every month, etc. You could conceptualize
עונה onah in a very different way. עונה onah could be conceptualized
as, a man is obligated to have sex with his wife whenever
she's interested in having sex. Right, you know, or right, or contextual,
but not by a calendar.
And there actually isn't, according to some פוסקים, poskim, that actually is
the דאורייתא de-Oraita מצוה mitzvah of עונה. onah. דרבנן de-Rabbanan is a
frequency, but דאורייתא de-Oraita it's based by context and whenever the wife
is interested, and it actually seems that there's an opinion of רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua that emphasizes that. So one way of reading רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer in the משנה, Mishnah, דברי רבי אליעזר, divrei Rabbi
Eliezer, is not this issue about how far can you be out
of the house when you have to go learn תורה Torah or
how long,
but it's a question about how do you conceptualize עונה? onah? Do
you conceptualize עונה onah as a calendar frequency, or do you conceptualize
it more sort of contextual? Okay, so that's just important to understand
in terms of the מצות עונה. mitzvat onah. But back to the
גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara says the opposing opinion is that if
you want to learn תורה, Torah, you can go out two or
three years. you don't need any special permission. אמר רבא Amar Rava
says רבא, Rava, סמכו רבנן אדרב אדא בר אהבה ועבדו עובדא בנפשייהו.
Samchu Rabanan ad’Rav Adda bar Ahava va’avdu uvda benafshayhu.
The students relied on רב אדא בר אהבה׳ס Rav Adda bar Ahava’s
articulation of who the חכמים Chachamim are, even though רב אדא בר
אהבה Rav Adda bar Ahava actually said we rule, oh he didn't
say, but he says the חכמים Chachamim
say two or three years, so the rabbinic students relied on his
articulation of the חכמים Chachamim's position and they פסקן pasken for themselves.
They allowed themselves to be out of the house. Okay, so ועבדו
עובדא בנפשייהו. va’avdu uvda benafshayhu. Now ועבדו עובדא בנפשייהו va’avdu uvda benafshayhu
could just mean they פסקן pasken for themselves, you know, in a
very sort of self-serving way. רש״י Rashi takes it even one step
further. רש״י Rashi says בנפשייהו benafshayhu means with their own souls. They
did that, but they risked their own lives in doing that. And
now we're going to have the story about the guy who was
too much out of the house and what happened to him. So
very nice you want to rely on that, but you're taking your
life in your own hands. Okay, כי הא דרב רחומי, Ki ha
de’Rav Rechumi, like the story of רב רחומי. Rav Rechumi. Right, again
the whole language of רחומי, Rechumi, רחמים, Rachamim, compassion.
הוה שכיח קמיה דרבא במחוזא. Hava shechiach kamei de’Rava be’Mechuza. He would
spend time with רבא Rava in מחוזא. Mechuza. הוה רגיל דהוה אתי
לביתיה כל מעלי יומא דכיפורי. Hava ragil de’hava ati le’veiteih kol ma’alei
yoma de’Kippuri. And he would come home once a year ערב יום
כיפור. Erev Yom Kippur. יומא חד משכתיה שמעתא, Yoma chad mashchateih shema’ta,
one day the learning stretched on. הוה מסכיא דביתהו, Hava maschia deveiteihu,
his wife was looking, השתא אתי, השתא אתי, Hashta ati, hashta ati,
now he's coming, now he's coming. ולא אתי, Vela ati, he didn't
come. חלש דעתה, Chalash da’ata, she grew, you know, despaired.
אחית דמעתא מעינה, Achit dima’ta me’eina, a tear dropped from her eye.
הוה יתיב באיגרא, Hava yativ be’igra, he was sitting on the roof.
איפחית איגרא מתותיה, Iphachit igra mituteih, so now you have another thing
collapsing underneath him. The roof collapsed underneath him. ונח נפשיה, Venach nafsheih,
and he died. So if you want to פסקן pasken like רב
אדא בר אהבה, Rav Adda bar Ahava, no, you're taking your life
into your own hands. Now by the way, רש״י, Rashi, so here
again you have the roof collapsing, how do you balance what you're
legally entitled to and your responsibilities, your moral responsibilities, etc. By the
way, the ראב״ד Ra’avad does not read the story that way, or
rather the ראב״ד Ra’avad ignores the implications of the story, and the
ראב״ד Ra’avad says ועבדו עובדא בנפשייהו va’avdu uvda benafshayhu not like רש״י,
Rashi, not like you're risking your own life. He just says yeah,
that's how they פסקן pasken and that's how we פסקן, pasken, that
you're allowed to be out of the house for two or three
years if you're going to learn תורה. Torah. So a lot of
different attitudes that extended, you know, up through today, you know, and
in the כולל Kollel world and so on, about how do you
strike this balance and which of the sort of different voices of
the גמרא, Gemara, you know, do you sort of, do you follow.
Okay, but again, interesting that the same רש״י Rashi that said שלא
ישא על חטא shelo yisa al cheit when you're even if you
get your wife to agree, here emphasized the word בנפשייהו benafshayhu meaning
sort of risking your own life if you choose to פסקן pasken
this way. Yes.
So in other words, the תלמוד Talmud does not, the תלמוד Talmud
disconnects in the משנה Mishnah רבי אליעזר׳ס Rabbi Eliezer’s position from the
ספנים, safanim, from the sailors.
Yes, it makes it all about the issue about the תורה Torah
student.
Right. And it looks like from the wording that there must have
been an opposing מחלוקת machloket opinion against רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, what
is that? Right, exactly, strictly contextual. Right, exactly.
And it does it on a much earlier statement in the משנה,
Mishnah, which is why I said that it's very possible that it's
really a question about what the מצות עונה Mitzvat Onah is and
how to conceptualize it, but that's not where the גמרא Gemara goes.
I'll just read you the הרא״ש Ha’Rosh in terms by the way
about this ועבדו עובדא בנפשייהו va’avdu uvda benafshayhu says, he says like
this: רב אלפס לא הביא דברי רב אדא בר אהבה משום דסבר
הלכה כרבי אליעזר.
Rav Alfas lo heivi divrei Rav Adda
bar Ahava mishum desavar halacha ke’Rabbi Eliezer. So the רי״ף Rif doesn't
bring it because he rules like רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, most you're
allowed to be out, you know, one month without רשות, reshut, not
the two or three years. והרמ״ה פסק כרב אדא בר אהבה, Ve’ha’Ramah
pasak ke’Rav Adda bar Ahava, no it wasn't
the ראב״ד Ra’avad it was הרמ״ה, ha’Ramah, מדקאמר סמכו רבנן אדרב אדא
בר
אהבה קעבדו עובדא בנפשייהו.
mide’ka’amar samchu Rabanan ad’Rav Adda bar
Ahava ka’avdu uvda benafshayhu. Okay. ואף על גב דהלכתא הכי הוא מבעי
לאגוני לנפשיה כל האי. Ve’af al gav dehilchata hachi hu mibaei le’agunei
lenafsheih kol hai. And then the ראב״ד Ra’avad tries to reintroduce the
sense of like legal rights
and moral responsibility. In principle he says we פסקן pasken you can
be out two or three years, but take a little bit of
a message from this story about the roof collapsing and try to
at least come home on time once a year ערב יום כיפור,
Erev Yom Kippur, okay, or something like that. So again the interesting
question about which of these various voices do we go like?
Yes. Interesting juxtaposition of the images, the floor collapsing, once the power
of one tear, yes,
causing the floor to collapse.
Right, it's dramatic, right.
The pathos of it all, feeling.
Right, it's a good point and you know, the idea of אנחה
שוברת גופו של אדם, anacha shoveret gufo shel adam, let's also remember
that, the sighing breaking a person's body. And here something else broke,
right, it was a little tear and it broke the floor. So
there's, yeah, there's definitely, yeah, definitely
the other breaking of course, all that
weight, where breaks.
Yeah, but they but they had the strength to to to overcome
it. To overcome it, exactly. All right. So did anyone just tell
the רמב״ם Rambam use this story?
And she just read it in a very, I mean, beautiful way.
She didn't use it, she I mean she just did a very
dramatic reading and interpretation of it. Okay. עונת תלמידי חכמים אימתי. Onat
talmidei chachamim eimatai.
What is the frequency What is the frequency of תורה Torah of
תורה Torah sages because it's not in the משנה. Mishna. The משנה
Mishna says they can be away once a month without permission. It
doesn't say what their normal עונה ona is.
So אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל: Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel: מערב
שבת לערב שבת. Me'erev Shabbos l'erev Shabbos. And ערב שבת erev Shabbos
here meaning Friday, meaning presumably Friday night, when people are at home
and they don't have to work and, as רש״י Rashi says, it's
also עונג שבת. oneg Shabbos. For the kabbalists there's a lot of
other importance about Friday night and so on. Okay. רש״י Rashi says
שהוא ליל תענוג ושביתה והנאת הגוף. shehu leil ta'anug u'shvita ve'hana'at haguf.
So it's part of עונג שבת, oneg Shabbos, also very important because,
right, for some of the sectarians in the בית שני Bayis Sheni
period, דווקא davka you weren't allowed to have sex on שבת, Shabbos,
it was a violation of שבת. Shabbos. And you remember we had
a whole discussion in the beginning of the מסכת maseches of having
sex for the first time שבת Shabbos night, and then it becomes
that שבת Shabbos night is the special
obligation of having sex or special opportunity. אשר פריו יתן בעתו, Asher
piryo yiten be'ito, the fruit is given in the right time. אמר
רב יהודה ואיתימא רב הונא ואיתימא רב נחמן: Amar Rav Yehuda ve'iseima
Rav Huna ve'iseima Rav Nachman: זה המשמש מטתו מערב שבת לערב שבת.
ze hamishamesh mitaso me'erev Shabbos l'erev Shabbos. That is the one that
has sex at the right times, at the regular intervals, Friday night
to Friday night, and therefore presumably that will also lead to the
proper conception of children, to the fruit being bear born in the
right time.
יהודה בריה דרבי חייא, Yehuda brei de'Rabbi Chiya, so Judah the son
of Rabbi Chiya, וחתניה דרבי ינאי, ve'chasnei de'Rabbi Yanai, the son-in-law of
Rabbi Yanai, הוה אזיל ויתיב בבי רב. hava azil ve'yasiv be'bei rav.
So here again we're getting to תלמוד תורה talmud Torah and being
at home. We're sitting in the house of his Rebbe. וכל בי
שמשי, Ve'chol bei shimshai, every ערב שבת, erev Shabbos, בי שמשי bei
shimshai literally means nightfall, בין השמשות, bein hashmashos, but תוספות Tosafot points
out the significant בין השמשות bein hashmashos during the week is the
Friday night בין השמשות. bein hashmashos. So every ערב שבת הוה אתי
לביתיה. erev Shabbos hava asi l'veiseih. He would come home. וכי הוה
אתי, Ve'chi hava asi, when he would come home, הוה קחזי עמודא
דנורא, hava kachazi amuda d'nura,
a pillar of fire would be seen preceding him. יומא חד משכתיה
שמעתא. Yoma chad mashcheih shema'ta. So one Friday he got involved in
his learning. כיון דלא חזי ההוא סימנא, Keivan d'lo chazi hahu simana,
since the people of his home, his wife, didn't see the sign,
the whatever, we'll see, his father-in-law, they didn't see the pillar coming,
אמר להו רבי ינאי, amar lehu Rabbi Yanai, so Rabbi Yanai who
was his father-in-law said to the members of the household: כפו מיטתו,
kifu mitasu, upturn your bed, which was the סימן siman of אבלות.
aveilus. שאלמלי יהודה קיים, She'ilmalei Yehuda kayam, if Yehuda had still been
alive, לא ביטל עונתו, lo bital onaso, he would not have shirked
his responsibilities and missed his time to be home with his wife.
So because he didn't see the pillar he assumed that his son-in-law
had died. Which hadn't happened. הוה כשגגה שיוצא מלפני השליט. Hava kishgaga
sheyotzei milifnei hashalit. It was like an error that came from the
presence of the ruler, which the גמרא Gemara says like you say
something wrong and you're an important person and it's going to come
true. ונח נפשיה, Ve'nach nafsheih, and Rav Yehuda died. So this is
interesting, right? This isn't even the sort of suffering of the wife.
This is just the fact that he wasn't doing his duty. Even
before you get to the wife's emotional response. Oh look, he would
never have shirked his duty and hence this consequence. Okay. And this
is just coming home not once a year, this is coming home
every ערב שבת. erev Shabbos. So again, very different types of messages
you can get based on which story you're reading.
רבי איעסק ליה לבריה בי רבי חייא. Rebbi i'asak leh l'vreih bei
Rebbi Chiya. Rebbi, Rebbi married off his son, Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi, to
the family of רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, to a daughter of רבי
חייא. Rabbi Chiya. כי מטא למכתב כתובה, Ki mta limchtav kesuvah, when
they came to write the כתובה, kesuvah, נח נפשה דרביתא, nach nafsha
d'rabisa, the daughter died, the bride died. אמר רבי: Amar Rebbi: חס
ושלום פסולי איכא? chas v'shalom psulei ika? Perhaps there is some invalidity,
meaning there's some reason, there's some problem with this wedding, which caused
the woman to die so that the wedding shouldn't go through. So
here the bride is the one that is suffering as a result
of some problem. Let's see what the problem was. יתיבו ועיינו במשפחות.
Yasivu ve'ayeinu bemishpachos. They went and they looked at the various lineage.
רבי אתי משפטיה בן אביטל. Rebbi asi mi'Shefatya ben Avital. Rebbi came
from Shefatya ben Avital. Avital was one of David's wives. So the
understanding that Rebbi was a descendant from בית דוד. Beis Dovid. ורבי
חייא אתי משמי אחי דוד. Ve'Rabbi Chiya asi mi'Shimi achi Dovid.
And Rabbi Chiya came from Shimi, David's brother. So they did not
both come from the royal family. Rabbi Chiya came from a little
bit of an offshoot of the royal family. So we see that
that was not a good יחוס, yichus, not a good marriage, since
he wasn't directly from the royal family. So that caused this poor
girl to die. So go figure.
Okay. אזל ואיעסק ליה לבריה בי רבי יוסי בן זמרא. Azal ve'i'asak
leh l'vreih bei Rabbi Yossi ben Zimra. Zimra, so he said: let's
try marrying him into a different family, him into a different family.
So he married him off into the family of Rabbi Yossi ben
Zimra. פסקו ליה תרתי סרי שנין Pasku leh tartai srei shanin דמיזיל
בבי רב. d'meizil be'bei rav. Now we're going to get back to
תלמוד תורה. talmud Torah. פסקו ליה תרתי סרי שנין Pasku leh tartai
srei shanin דמיזיל בבי רב. d'meizil be'bei rav. So they ruled for
him that the deal they made with the כלה's kallah family is
that they would support him for 12 years in ישיבה yeshiva before
he had to get married. Okay. He would have the right to
go learn for 12 years in ישיבה, yeshiva, probably on the כלה's
kallah father's dime until the wedding. Okay. So maybe. after the נישואין
nissuin or something. תריסר שנין למיזל בבי רב. Treisar shanin l'meizal bevei
rav. So they, so the כלה's Kallah family wanted to get things
moving a little faster even though they made that deal. So what
did they do? אחלפו קמיה, Achlapu kammai, they had the bride walk
in front of him. You sure you want to wait?
So אמר להו, Amar lehu, so then he said, you know what,
נהוי שית שנין, Nava shish shanin, maybe I'll just go to ישיבה
Yeshiva for six years. אחלפו קמיה, Achlapu kammai, they had her walk
in front of him again. So אמר להו, Amar lehu, he said,
you know what, איכנס, Ichnis, maybe I'll get married now, והדר איזיל,
V'hadar eizil, and then I'll go. By the way, notice that this
was the ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael approach. The ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
approach, as I said before, is don't go ahead and get married
and then learn תורה. Torah. If you're going to be spending all
your time learning תורה, Torah, do it before you get married. Once
you get married, then you have those domestic responsibilities. You can't shirk
them. So anyway, so that's what he was going to learn תורה
Torah first, but then he finally agreed to go ahead and get
married first. Now, what's he going to do now that he's married?
Is he going to spend all his time in ישיבה? Yeshiva? והדר
איזיל. V'hadar eizil. And then so איכנס והדר איזיל, Ichnis v'hadar eizil,
so he got married first and then he went, but presumably once
he got married and then he's going to learn, he's not exactly
devoting the same amount of time to learn, right? That's the whole
point in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, you can't abandon your wife once
you're married. So הוה קא מיכסיף מאבוה. Havah kamikhsif me'avuah. He was
embarrassed from his father because his father wanted him to spend 12
years learning in ישיבה Yeshiva before he got married. So אמר ליה,
Amar leh, so his father said to him, בני, Bni, my son,
דעת קונך יש בך. Da'as koncha yesh becha. You're like your Creator.
You know, you're thinking the way your Creator thought. מעיקרא כתיב, Me'ikara
ksiv, as I already said, by the שירת הים, Shirat HaYam, תביאמו
ותטעמו בהר נחלתך, T'vi'eimo v'sita'eimo behar nachalatcha, right? You'll go into the
land and then you'll build a בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash on that
mountain. So they first were going to wait before they got married,
before they started living together, they would have to go into the
land and then have the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash there. ולסוף כתיב,
U'lesof ksiv, but then God was so eager to get things going
that it says ועשו לי מקדש ושכנתי בתוכם, V'asu li mikdash v'shachanti
b'tocham, that you have the marriage much sooner right after, you know,
right after מתן תורה. Matan Torah. So, you know, so don't feel
so bad, it's okay, you know, that you wanted to do this.
Now, so he did, he got married. His father wasn't as upset
as he was afraid his father would be. But he's still going
to go off and learn in ישיבה. Yeshiva. אזיל יתיב תריסר שני
בבי רב. Azil yasiv treisar shnei bevei rav.
So he went and he learned for 12 years. Okay, which maybe
he shouldn't have done because once he got married maybe he'd be
spending more time at home. It sounds like he completely left his
wife behind and now we're going to find out that's exactly what
happened.
עד דאתא איעקרא דביתהו. Ad d'ata itkar d'vattayhu. His wife had become
sterile, so presumably he wasn't having sex with her during that time,
he had abandoned his own obligation. So he sort of wanted the
best of both, which was the בבלי Bavli approach, which isn't approved
of in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Get married, right, you know, and
then abandon your wife and go and learn תורה. Torah. You know,
so if he was going to get married, he should have spent
more time at home. So look what happened. So אמר רב, Amar
Rav, so רב Rav said, היכי נעביד? Heichi navid? What can we
do? נגרשה, Nigrisha, should he divorce her in order to marry another
woman to have kids? יאמרו, Yomru, ענייה זו לשוא שימרה? Ani azo
l'shav shimra?
So the people will say, this poor woman for nothing she waited
for 12 years? נינסב איתתא אחריתי, Ninsa itta achrita, maybe he should
marry another wife to have kids and keep married to the first
one, which by the way, you can so tell this is done
through a בבלי Bavli lens because in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they
did not marry two wives. Okay, should he marry another wife? So
יאמרו, Yomru, זו אשתו וזו זונתו. Zu ishto v'zu zonoso. They'll say,
this one is his real wife and this first one, this is
like his prostitute. That's also not appropriate. So but so there's no
solution, so you know what? בעא רחמי ואיתסיאת. Ba'ei lei rachamei v'isis.
So רב Rav prayed for her and she got cured. Which by
the way is again interesting, which sort of is like, okay, you
abandoned his wife, it led to some problems, but you know what?
There are solutions, right? So we're not ignoring the problems, but we'll
find a solution. Like the אייבערשטער Eibishter will help. Okay, and that's
and we'll see another story just like this again very much sort
of shaped by the בבלי, Bavli, acknowledging some of the problems but
in the end feeling that there are solutions to these problems. So
let's take a look. רבי חנינא בן חכינאי Rabbi Chanina ben Chachinai
הוה קאזיל לבי רב. havah ka'azil l'vei rav. רבי חנינא בן חכינאי
Rabbi Chanina ben Chachinai was going to his רבי's Rebbe house to
the ישיבה Yeshiva בשלהי הילולא דרבי שמעון בר יוחאי b'shilhei hillula d'Rabbi
Shimon bar Yochai at the end of the wedding week or party
of רבי שמעון בר יוחאי. Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai. אמר ליה, Amar
leh, so רבי שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai said to
him, אקיב לי עד דאתי ואזיל בהדך. Akiv li ad d'asi v'azil
b'adhach. Wait for me, wait for the wedding to be over and
then you know then I'll come with you to the ישיבה. Yeshiva.
I spent the week getting married now it's time to leave the
house and come with you. Again this is ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
here. So it's but told through the בבלי Bavli lens. לא עכב
ליה, Lo akiv leh, he didn't wait for him. אזיל יתיב תריסר
שני בבי רב. Azil yasiv treisar shnei bevei rav. And then this
רבי, Rabbi, so we don't hear anything more about רבי שמעון בר
יוחאי, Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai, presumably it was a good thing that
he didn't wait for him because רבי שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon
bar Yochai then wound up spending a little bit more time at
home. But this רבי חנינא בן חכינאי, Rabbi Chanina ben Chachinai, he
now went to learn in ישיבה Yeshiva and he there was for
there for 12 years בבי רב bevei rav עד דאתי אישתנין ad
d'asi ishtanun עד דאתי ad d'asi by the time he finally came
back to his. to his home after having been away for 12
years, אשתנו שבילי דמתא. ishtannu shivilei d'massa. So all the roads had
changed and sort of like that whole story about what's-his-name who fell
asleep for how 70 years. Right. Okay.
ולא ידע למיזל לביתיה, v'lo yada le-meizal l'beiseih, he didn't know how
to get home. אזל יתיב אגודא דנהרא, azal yasiv agudda d'nahara, he
sat by the sort of by the bank of the river.
שמע להו רויבתא, shama lehu ravista, he heard a young woman דהוו
קרו לה בת חכינאי, d'havu karu lah bas Chachinai, that people would
call her the daughter of Chachinai. So בת חכינאי. bas Chachinai. So
they say to her, בת חכינאי בת חכינאי מלי קולתך ותא ניזיל,
bas Chachinai bas Chachinai malli kulskha v'sa nizil, go fill your basket
and let's get going. אמר שמע מינה האי רויבתא דידן, amar shema
mina hai ravista didan, yeah this girl is ours, meaning this is
my daughter. אזל בתרה, azal basrah, he followed her. הוה יתבה דביתהו,
hava yasva d'vasaihu, his wife was sitting, קנא לה קמחא, kana lah
kamcha,
so she was like doing stuff with flour. דל עיניה, dal eineih,
lift up her eyes, חזיתיה, chazishei, and all of a sudden she
saw her husband who had been away for 12 years.
So שביי ליבה, savyei libba, so her heart sort of caught her
heart, you know like her heart jumped out at her. פרח רוחה,
parach rucha, she fainted, her her you know her spirit departed. אמר
לפניו, amar lefanav, so and she apparently she died out of shock.
So God, so he said, ריבונו של עולם, Ribbono Shel Olam, ענייה
זו, aniya zo, this poor woman, זה שכרה, zeh secharah, this is
her reward? בעא רחמי עלה וחית, ba'ei rachamei alah v'chyas, he prayed
for her and she was resuscitated. Okay, so again, so again you
have very different than the roof falling in and dying. Right here,
and that was just now, here they're away for 12 years, right,
for a super-extended period. Maybe they shouldn't be, like you know, the
guy, you know, leaving the guy at the wedding party a little
bit had that image of, you know, maybe you should sort of
be with your wife and not be abandoning your wife or whatever,
the whole thing about making an arrangement, you don't get married and
then leave, and they went ahead and they did it. But at
the end of the day, there was some solution. Yes, there could
be bad things that come as a result, but maybe they can
also some, it's like there's mixed messages here about this. Okay, let's
keep on going, let's see the next story. And it says the
woman
was resuscitated and in the other case the man died.
Yeah,
you're right too.
בעא רחמי ba'ei rachamei on the woman.
You know, that's an excellent point. You're absolutely correct that even sort
of the tragic part of this story, it's like the man isn't
suffering for his תלמוד תורה, Talmud Torah, you know, you're 100 percent
correct. Not only is this sort of undercutting the message in the
fact that there's a solution, but even if it hadn't been solved,
it would have been the woman that would have suffered, not the
man. The man isn't suffering for his, it's not fair, but in
the end even the man isn't suffering for his תלמוד תורה. Talmud
Torah. So yeah, you're right. So these stories obviously are shifting, though
thank you, that's an excellent point. So these stories are really sort
of shifting the whole, you know, sense of like is it the
right thing to do or not the right thing to do.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, רבי חמא בר ביסא
אזל יתיב תריסר שני בבי מדרשא, Reb Chama bar Bissa azal yasiv
treisar shani b'vei midrasha, so
רבי חמא בר ביסא Reb Chama bar Bissa spent 12 years in
the בית מדרש. beis medrash. כי אתא, ki ata, when it was
time to come home, אמר, amar, he said, לא אעביד כרבי חנינא
בן חכינאי, lo e'evid k'rabbi Chanina ben Chachinai, I'm not going to
do like רבי חנינא בן חכינאי Rabbi Chanina ben Chachinai did where
he surprised his wife and she died as a result. עייל יתיב
במדרשא, ayal yasiv b'midrasha,
so he sat in the ישיבה, yeshiva, maybe in his home hometown.
שלח לביתיה, shelach l'beiseih,
and he sent to his home, אתא רבי אושעיא, ata Reb Oshaya,
שלח לביתיה, shelach l'beiseih, that he was about to return. Okay, so
he let them know that he was coming back so he didn't
shock his wife. אתא רבי אושעיא בריה, ata Reb Oshaya brei,
his son came. יתיב קמיה yasiv kamei and sat in front of
him, came to the בית מדרש beis medrash maybe at the outskirts
of the town and and started learning with him. Now as we're
going to see, he didn't introduce himself as his son, this guy's
been away for 12 years. הוה קא מצאלי ליה שמעתא, hava ka
matzlei lei shematsa, and he was asking him like a you know
from סוגיות sugyas in the גמרא, Gemara, right? הוה קא חזי דקא
מחדדי שמעתיה, hava ka chaza d'ka midadai shematsateih,
he saw that he was a that this young man was very
sharp and he really knew his learning. חלש דעתיה, chalash da'ateih,
he grew weak, he like his you know he despaired.
אמר, amar, אי הואי הכא, i havai hacha, if I had stayed
at home, הוה לי זרעא כי האי, havai li zara ki hai,
I would have had a I would have been able to you
know to educate my son and I would have had a son
as sharp as this guy. Of course it was his son, he
didn't realize. על לביתיה, al l'beiseih, he came into his home. על
בריה, al breih, so his son came after, you know, entered in
after him. Again, he didn't know his son. קם קמיה, kam kamei,
so he saw this young man who was so sharp and he
entered this big תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham and he entered into the
home, so he stood up you know in his presence. הוא סבר
למשאל שמעתא קא בעי, hu savar l'mishal shematsa ka baei, he thought
that he was coming to do more learning. So אמר לה דביתהו,
amar lah d'vassaihu, his wife said to him, מי איכא אבא דקאי
מקמי ברא, mi ika abba d'kai mikmei bera, is there a father
that stands for his son? So now he realized it was his
son. קרא ליה רמי בר חמא, kara lei Rami bar Chama, so
רבי חמא Reb Chama said about him, החוט המשולש לא במהרה ינתק,
hachut hameshulash lo bimehera yinateik, the three-bound cord, you know, threefold cord
will not easily break. זה רבי אושעיא בנה של רבי חמא בר
ביסא, zeh Reb Oshaya bena shel Reb Chama bar Bissa, this is
רבי אושעיא Reb Oshaya the son of רבי חמא בר
ביסא Reb Chama bar Bissa and רבי ביסא Reb Bissa was also
a huge תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham and now you know the תורה
Torah will remain through them through the generations. Notice again, you go
away, you think that it's maybe you're not living up to your
responsibilities cause you're not home to educate your kids. But look, here
in this story, he wasn't home to educate his kids and his
kids grew up to be a big תלמיד חכם talmid chacham anyway.
So the message of these other stories are a little bit like
don't worry so much. Obviously it's not like you can just completely
ignore it, there are concerns, your kids' education, your wife, etc. But
notice by the way, it's not a problem that you're away for
12 years. The only problem was that maybe in the- you shocked
your wife when you returned, or maybe she in the interim she
was no longer able to have kids. But the actual absence itself,
again, and as was very well pointed out, even when something bad
happens, it doesn't happen to you. So these last stories are very
different than some of the earlier stories.
Okay, I think that there's a sadness to this text because he
didn't recognize his son. You would say I'm bringing that to...
No,
is there a sadness?
Yeah, there's a sadness, it's sad.
Right.
Yeah, look at that, look he turned out to be a big
תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. החוט המשולש לא במהרה ינתק. hachut hameshulash lo
bimehera yinatek. In the end maybe there was a momentary sadness, but
the basic message is wasn't such a bad- it was no problem
that you were away for 12 years. Okay, now we get to
the famous story of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Up till now it's
been 12 years, now we get to 24 years. Let's see if
we can make it to the משנה. Mishnah. We'll have to read
this pretty quickly. Okay, רבי עקיבא רעיא דבן כלבא שבוע הוה. Rabbi
Akiva raya de-Ben Kalba Savua hava. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was the
shepherd of כלבא שבוע. Kalba Savua. חזיתיה ברתיה דהוה צניעא ומעלי. chaziteih
barteih de-hava tznia u-mali.
He saw, or כלבא שבוע's Kalba Savua daughter saw, that he was
modest and of high quality, good character traits.
אמרה ליה, amrah leih, she said to him,
clearly he was interested in her and he lets that be known,
so she said to him, אי מקדשנא לך, im makdishana lach, if
I agree to marry you, אזלת לבי רב, azlat levei rav, will
you go and study in yeshiva? אמר לה אין, amar lah in,
he said yes. איקדשלה בצינא, ikdashalah betzina, so he married her in
private, ושדרתיה, veshadrateih,
and she sent him off to learn in yeshiva. שמע אבוה, shama
avuh, the father heard, אפקה מביתיה, afkeih mibeiteih,
he kicked her out of the house because she married this ignoramus.
אדרה נמי נכסי, adrah nami neichasei, and כלבא שבוע Kalba Savua was
very wealthy and once he found out that his daughter married this
ignoramus, he took a vow to forbid her from getting any benefit
from all of his wealth. אזל יתיב תריסר שנין. azal yativ treisar
shanin. Now רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva went and he was learning for
12 years בבי רב be-bei rav in the yeshiva. כי אתא, ki
ata, when he returned, אייתי בהדיה תריסר סרי אלפי תלמידי. aisi badeih
treisar srei alfei talmidei. He brought 12,000 students. שמעיה לההוא סבא דקאמר
לה, shamaiah le-hahu saba de-ka'amar lah, so he heard, as he was
about to come home, he heard an old
woman, an old man telling her, עד כמה קמבדרת אלמנות חיות, ad
kama kamitbartat almanut chayut,
until how long will you live the life of a living widow,
with your husband off in yeshiva and you are all alone? אמרה
ליה, amrah leih, so she said back to this old guy, אי
לדידי ציית, i ledidi tzaias, if my husband would listen to me,
יתיב תריסר שני אחריני, yativ treisar shani achrinei, he would only stay
there for 12 more years. אמר, amar, so רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
overheard this and he said,
ברשות קעבידנא.
bi-reshut
ka-avadna. Oh, she's okay with it. Now by the way, תוספות Tosafot
points out, in a way this is the important shift from the
beginning and the end, not just different opinions, that in the end
it's like the wife really wants the husband at home and maybe
he can persuade her to be away, right? And the wife is
there longing for the husband and he's not coming, she's crying. And
then at the end, maybe some of the difference of the stories
are not just difference of attitudes, but also difference about what the
wife really feels. Like the last story we're left with is one
where they're truly partners in this, where she truly does want him
to be learning in yeshiva. That's true with a lot of כולל
kollel wives, right? They really want their husband, you don't have to
persuade them. Prestige or whatever. Now of course how much is that
shaped by the culture that you're in is a different question, but
these end stories are not just maybe the גמרא Gemara saying is
it right or not right, but also how is the wife, how
much is she a very active participant in this? Okay, so he
should only be the 12 more years. So הדר אזל ויתיב תריסר
שני אחריני, hadar azal ve-yativ treisar shani achrinei, he went back, he
didn't even say hello to her, turned around and went back another
12 years בבי רב be-bei rav in the yeshiva. כי הוי אתי
אייתי בהדיה עשרין וארבעה אלפי תלמידי. ki hava ati aisi badeih esrin
ve-arba alfei talmidei. Now he's coming back with 24,000 students. שמעת דבתיה
הות קנפקא לאפיה, shamat devataih havat kanpaka la-apeih,
his wife heard and she came out to greet him. אמרו לה
שיבבתא, amru lah sheveivata,
so her neighbor said to her, שאילי מאני לבושי ואיכסי, shili mani
levushei ve-ichasi, go borrow some nice clothes to greet your husband. אמרה
להו, amrah lehu, so she said to them, יודע צדיק נפש בהמתו,
yodea tzaddik nefesh behemto,
the righteous man knows the soul of his beast, of his animal.
So again, talking about partnership and here she's describing herself as an
animal, so one wonders about that. Of course her name is רחל,
Rachel, so one wonders if that's also relevant. Yes, but still, it
strikes a discordant note at least. It makes her very subservient here,
very. כי מטא לגביה, ki mata legabeih,
when she came to him, נפלה על אפה, nafla al apa, she
fell on her face, קמנשקה. ka-menashka.
he was kissing his legs, הוה קא מנחיף לה שמעיה *hava ka-manchif
lah shamaiya*, so his attendant was pushing her off, it was unseemly.
אמר להו *amar lehu*, he said to the, he said to them,
שבקוה *shabkuna*, let her be, שלי ושלכם שלה הוא *sheli ve-shelachem shelah
hu*, everything that's mine and yours is all hers. So again it's
back to that sense of like this
partnership and she's an equal partner in this whole thing. שמע אבוה
דאתא גברא רבא *shama avua de-asa gavra raba*, the father heard that
this big תלמיד חכם *talmid chacham* came למתא *le-masa* to the city.
אמר *amar*, he said, איזיל לגביה *izel gabei*, let me go greet
him. אפשר דמפי נדראי *epsher de-mafei nidrai*, maybe he'll annul my vow
that I made to forbid. Now he didn't realize that this was
רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*, his daughter's husband, but he said now but
he was in a place where he wanted to annul the vow
that he made to forbid his daughter to get benefit from his
wealth, his son-in-law. אתא לגביה *atei le-gabei*, he went to him. אמר
ליה *amar lei*, so רבי
עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* said to him without letting him know yet who
he was, אדעתא דגברא רבא מי נדרת *adaata de-gavra raba mina narta*,
when you forbade her to get benefit from all of your wealth,
was that even assuming that she would marry somebody who would become
a big תלמיד חכם *talmid chacham*? אמר ליה *amar lei*, so he
said back, no, אפילו פרק אחד אפילו הלכה אחת *afilu perek echad
afilu halacha achas*, even if she would marry a guy that would
know how to learn like one chapter, one הלכה *halacha*, I would
have been happy, I wouldn't have made that vow. אמר ליה *amar
lei*, so he said to him, אנא הוא *ana hu*, I am
the man that she married. נפל אפי *naful apei*, he fell on
his face ונשקיה על כרעיה *venashkei al karei*, so like his daughter
did, he's kicking him, kissing him on his feet, ויהב ליה פלגא
מממוניה *veyaiv lei palga mi-mamonei*, and gave him half of his wealth.
So now you see that in the end you go away and
learn for twenty-four years, and if your wife agrees to it, it
all ends well. You wind up with wealth, with students and all
the whole thing, so that's a very different type of a message
that we're ending with. Okay, ברתיה דרבי עקיבא עבדא ליה לבן עזאי
הכי *barteih de-Rabbi Akiva avdah lei le-Ben Azai hachi*. Now the daughter
of רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* made the same deal with בן עזאי
*Ben Azai*. There are different versions of whether בן עזאי *Ben Azai*
ever got married because בן עזאי *Ben Azai* was תורתו אומנותו *toraso
u-mnaso*, but anyway, here she made the same deal with בן עזאי
*Ben Azai*, רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*'s daughter. והיינו דאמרי אינשי *ve-hainu d'amrei
inshi*, and that's what people say, רחילה בתר רחילה אזלא *racheila
basar racheila azla*, one sheep follows the lamb because רבי עקיבא *Rabbi
Akiva*'s wife's name was רחל *Rachel*. Okay, כעובדי אמא כך עובדי ברתא
*ke-ovdei ima kach ovdei barta*,
like the mother so the daughter. רב יוסף בריה דרבא *Rav Yosef
bereih de-Rava*, רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* the son of רבא *Rava*, שדריה
אבוהי לבי רב *shadrei avuhei le-vei rav*, his father sent him to
the Rebbe's house, לקמיה דרב יוסף *lekamei de-Rav Yosef*, to learn in
the ישיבה *Yeshiva* of רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*. פסקו ליה שית שני
*pasku lei sheish shani*, as opposed to twelve years, they agreed to
have him learn there for six years. כי הוה תלת שני מטא
מעלי יומא דכיפורי *ki hava tlas shani mata maali yoma de-kippurai*, at
the end of three years it was ערב יום כיפור *Erev Yom
Kippur*, so he was away from his home for three years. אמר
*amar*, maybe I should go home a little bit early to visit
once in three
years, before my six years are up. שמע אבוהי *shama avuhi*, שקל
מנא *shakol mana*, so the father heard that his son was coming
back before the six years were up, so he took a like
a weapon, ונפיק לאפיה *ve-nafik le-appei*, and went out to fight against
him, saying how dare you come home, you're supposed to be learning
six years straight. אמר ליה *amar lei*, זונחתא נזכרת *zonachta nizkarta*? What,
you remembered your prostitute? Meaning you're
so much thinking about sex that you had to come home before
your six years were up. איכא דאמרי *ika de-amrei*, some say אמר
ליה *amar lei*, יונחתא נזכרת *yonachta nizkarta*, you remembered your dove, so
that was obviously not as derogatory, but still saying get back to
ישיבה *Yeshiva*, you're supposed to learn for six years straight. אטריד *itrid*,
so they got distracted, לא מר אפסק ולא מר אפסק *lo mar
ifsach ve-lo mar ifsach*, neither of them had a chance to eat
their סעודה מפסקת *seudah mafsekes* and to eat before יום כיפור *Yom
Kippur*. So again this tie in with יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*, but
notice again as opposed to the story where the guy problem he
didn't come back before יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* and he died as
a result, here the guy wanted to come back on ערב יום
כיפור *Erev Yom Kippur* and he was told get back to ישיבה
*Yeshiva*. By the way, I just have to end by saying that
in ישיבות *Yeshivas* they like to quote this story, I remember when
I was first year in ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* and they said
not to go home בין הזמנים *bein hazmanim*, why shouldn't you go
home בין הזמנים *bein hazmanim* because רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* was coming
there at the end of 12 years, okay he was going to
go back to ישיבה *Yeshiva*, but spend a minute and say hi
to your wife, you haven't seen her in 12 years, or this
last story, okay come home for a day and go back. So
the answer is 12 years and 12 years is not the same
as 24 years.
And with that we will end for today.